<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The nevve and admirable arte of setting of corne with all the necessarie tooles and other circumstances belonging to the same: the particular titles whereof, are set downe in the page following.</title>
            <author>Plat, Hugh, Sir, 1552-1611?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1600</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09729</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19993.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103552</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839304</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839304</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3712</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09729)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3712)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1607:39)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The nevve and admirable arte of setting of corne with all the necessarie tooles and other circumstances belonging to the same: the particular titles whereof, are set downe in the page following.</title>
                  <author>Plat, Hugh, Sir, 1552-1611?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Peter Short, dwelling at the figure of the Starre on Bredstreet hill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1600.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Sir Hugh Plat.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴.</note>
                  <note>"A2r line 1 of text ends: "probablie", line 3 has "new"; C1r line 7 of text ends "cause", line 11 has "wormes"."--STC.</note>
                  <note>With woodcut title vignette.</note>
                  <note>Another edition of STC 19993.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Horticultural crops --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Planting (Plant culture) --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3712:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The nevv and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Arte of ſetting of Corne: With all the neceſſarie Tooles and other Circumſtances belonging to the ſame: the particular titles whereof, are ſet downe in the Page following.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>ADAMS TOOLE REVIVED</head>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <head>Magnus Deus in minimis.</head>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>Peter Short,</hi> dwelling at the <hi>ſigne of the Starre on Bredſtreet hill.</hi> 1600.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:3712:2"/>
            <head>The Contents of this Booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1</hi> How this inuention began.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2</hi> The reaſon why Corne doth ſhoote vp into ſo many eares rather by ſetting then ſowing.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3</hi> The maner of digging and laying of the arable grounds in this new practiſe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4</hi> The ſeuerall inſtruments for making the holes for the graine, and couering them.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5</hi> At what depth and diſtance your corne muſt be ſet.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6</hi> Whether it be good to fill the holes with common earth, and to prepare the ſeed before it be ſet.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7</hi> How to make choice of your ſeede corne.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8</hi> The difference of yeeld betweene the plough and the ſpade, with ſome new addition to the plough.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:3712:2"/>
            <head>The new found Arte of ſetting of Corne.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 1.</hi> How this inuention began.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Eere I maie rather probablie coniecture then certainly deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine howe this new conceit in ſetting of graine began. Happily ſome ſilly wench hauing a fewe cornes of wheate, mixed with ſome other ſeed, and being care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe of the vvorke ſhee had in hand, might nowe and then in ſteed of a Raddiſh or Carret ſeede, let fall a wheate corne into the ground, which after braunching it ſelfe into many eares, and yeelding ſo great encreaſe, gaue iuſt occaſion of ſome farther triall. Peraduenture the great and rich fertil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie that doth vſually happen in the ſetting of beanes and peaſe, might ſtirre vp ſome practiſing wit or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to make the like experience in wheate and barley. Or who knoweth whether that Enigmatical marriage betweene <hi>Bacchus</hi> and <hi>Ceres</hi> ſo cloſely couched in ſuch figuratiue termes by <hi>Iohan. Baptiſta Porta,</hi> in his <hi>Magia naturalis</hi> in the percloſe of his title, <hi>de nouis plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis producendis,</hi> might giue ſome light vnto this new and late inuention of ours. And laſtly, I haue beene
<pb facs="tcp:3712:3"/>credibly enformed that this manner of pricking in of corne, hath by the publike impreſſion of an ancient writer (whoſe name I cannot yet obtaine) euen in plaine and naked termes beene long ſince diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and manifeſted to the view of each reader. But it ſhall not greatly skill from whence this profitable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe had his firſt beginning (although for the honour of my countrie, I could wiſh the ſame were fronted with the name and title of an Engliſh Authour) and that as it hath pleaſed the great God of heauen in his vnſpeakeable mercie and loue, and in theſe times of dearth and penurie, to offer a moſt plentifull en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of our beſt nouriſhing, Manna vnto vs: ſo that wee may in all dutifull manner, with one heart and voice together, giue all thankes, honour, and praiſe vnto ſo great and bountiful a benefactor, whoſe name is glorious in the heauens, and whoſe mightie power extendeth it ſelfe ouer the face of the whole earth, <hi>cui laus in ſaecula ſaeculorum. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 2.</hi> The reaſon why Corne doth ſhoote vp into ſo many eares rather by ſetting then ſowing.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He conſideration hereof may well deſerue to be handled in the ſecond place, in my opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, both <hi>quia turpe eſt Philoſopho quidquam ſine ratione proferre,</hi> as <hi>Tully</hi> holdeth: and alſo for that it is a principall motiue to ſtirre vp a number of drowſie wittes to the practiſe hereof; who not as yet finding or conceiting any ſenſible reaſon for the ſame, are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther content with the fly-bitten and leane iades, to liue or ſtarue vpon the bare common, then by ſeeking
<pb facs="tcp:3712:3"/>out of better paſture, to gather more fleſh vpon their backes, and to grow in better liking in the ſight of all that ſhall behold them. Such winter Corne then as is vſually ſowne before or about Alhallownetide, in my poore reaſon, muſt of neceſſitie looſe a great part of his generatiue vertue, and radicall humiditie, both by the extreme nipping of the colde Northren and Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterly winds, and the bitter froſts and hayle, together with the great aboundance of the colde rayny ſhow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, which in the VVinter ſeaſon doe ſo plentifully attach and fall vppon the Grayne, lying then eyther naked and bare to all weather, or verie ſlenderly clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with a poore and thinne garment, not able ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fientlie to defende the inwarde and ſecrete fire of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, from ſuch outward and piercing enemies; yea, though it haue taken roote, and gotten ſome head before this boyſterous weather doe happen, yet by reaſon that the roote is ſhallowe, and hath taken ſo ſlender holde in the grounde, eyther the inward <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſamum</hi> is waſhed awaie with moyſture, or nipped with extreme colde, that it cannot poſſiblie ſend forth ſo manie ſpiring ſtalkes and eares as naturallie it would; beſides, the earth being full of clods, and not ſufficientlie broken into a fyne moulde with the Plough, the Corne cannot ſo eaſilie and plentifully by this attractiue nature drawe for his owne nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſuch ſtore of that vegetatiue ſalt from the earth, as it deſireth; the vertue and ſtrength whereof is more at large handled in my Booke of husbandry, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Anno 1594. and in that learned diſcourſe of M. <hi>Bernard Paliſsie,</hi> in his Booke intituled, <hi>Des eaux &amp; Fonteines.</hi> But on the other ſide, when as the cornes of wheate ſhall ly ſo deepe within their true and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall
<pb facs="tcp:3712:4"/>bed, euen their owne mothers belly, the earth being made ſo hollow &amp; open with the ſpade, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they may alſo draw ſufficient nouriſhment at their pleaſure, then are all theſe outwarde and iniurious ſtormes of haile and raine, ſo ſufficiently defended by this armour of proofe, as that the corne hauing his true and naturall putrifaction (being not perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med without the helpe of a kindly heate) doth after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in his due ſeaſon bring forth that infinite mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplication, whereof we haue had ſo many and rich experiments of late, farre beyond all the hopes and harueſts of all our predeceſſors.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 3.</hi> The manner of digging and laying of the arable grounds in this new practiſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen and how to digge, weed, or trench your grounds with the ſpade, is a matter ſo triuial and well knowne already to euerie countrie <hi>Coridon,</hi> as that I hold it not a fit ſubiect for a Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers penne, and therefore here I muſt referre you to thoſe beaten pathes, wherein euerie ſimple Garde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner hath walked a long time: onely the depth of digging, and true laying of the ground, ſeemes to be materiall in this our new kind of husbandry. Some in this late practiſe, by their experience commend the breaking vp of the ground a foote and a halfe deepe, and ſome two foote, and ſome but one foote; but in my opinion ſince that, three, or foure, or fiue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches at the moſt is a ſufficient depth for the corne to lie in, I ſee no reaſon but that eight or twelue inches more, is a depth ſufficient for the corne to roote in.
<pb facs="tcp:3712:4"/>This being graunted, then ſhall you haue this far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther benefite enſuing, that at the next breaking vp and digging of your grounde, you ſhall turne vppe ſuch moulde, as hath not ſpent his ſtrength in the former croppe, the fruite whereof you ſhall find in the next harueſt. And heere I muſt of neceſſitie acknowledge that M. <hi>Tauerner</hi> in his Booke of Experiments, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Fiſh and Fruit, being of this yeares date, hath bereaued mee of one of my beſt obſeruations in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard groundes, the ignorance whereof I hold to bee one of the ſpeciall and principall cauſes that ſo many of our Engliſh Orchards do neuer yeeld fruite anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to our charge and trauell: the ſecret whereof is this brieflie. Euerie ground hath naturallie an vpper cruſt of earth, which by the liuelie and viuifying heate of the Sunne, the comfortable nature of the Aire, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the congelatiue part of the raine (for ſo M. <hi>Bernard Paliſsie</hi> termeth it, being the firſt Author of a fift element) which often falleth vpon the ground, is made more rich and fruitefull than all the reſidue of the earth beſides, which vpper cruſt in ſome ground is a foot, in ſome two, and in ſome three foot deepe, and in ſome not aboue halfe a foot. And vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame vpper cruſt is eyther a hote chalke, a drie ſand, a barren grauell, or a cold leane claie or lome, or ſuch like. It is therefore requiſite that you ſet your young trees in ſuch ſort, as that the rootes may runne and ſpreade within that vpper cruſt: and if you ſet them deeper, they may happily grow, but neuer bring forth fruit in any plentifull manner: nay, though the earth ſhould conſiſt of one and the ſelfe ſame veine, and of one colour and nature in ſhewe, yet becauſe the Sun doth not giue his impreſſion nor digeſtion
<pb facs="tcp:3712:5"/>vnto the earth, but to a certaine depth (which I gueſſe not much to exceede two foote) you ſhall finde that all the reſt of the mould vnder that depth wil be leane and hungrie, not hauing anie ſtrength or fatnes in it. And this is the reaſon why ſuch earth as hath beene digged out of vaultes and Cellers, not hauing recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued anie life or comfort from the Sunne beames, though of neuer ſo blacke and rich moulde in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward apparance, if it be ſpread vpon garden grounds, doth make them vtterly barren and vnfruitfull. That which is heere ſpoken of Orchard groundes, I would haue all wiſe and skilfull husband-men to applie alſo to their Corne groundes, that in anie caſe they neuer digge deeper with the Spade, then the ſtrength of the ground will beare, and ſo by their ignorance diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite a work and practiſe of ſo great expectation. Now concerning the laying of your groundes, eyther in ridges and furrowes, or in a declining leuell, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the raine maie haue a ſufficient conueyance, after they haue once receiued their due moiſture from the cloudes: this reſteth in the diſcretion of the husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, who beſt knoweth the moiſture or dryneſſe of his owne groundes, and accordingly may giue ſuch a current vnto them, as may beſt fit the ſeueral natures of each ground or ſoyle. And heere I may not omit that eaſe and ſpeed in breaking vp of groundes, which ſome of our late practiſers haue found out, by making the firſt entrance with a deepe cutting plough, and then purſuing the ſame with the ſpade, whereby much charge, labour, and expence of time is auoided.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:3712:5"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 4.</hi> The ſeuerall inſtruments for making the holes for the graine, and couering them.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is an olde ſaying, that handes were made before kniues: and I doubt not, but the ſame may aſwell be verified in tooles. For to my rememberance, the firſt man that euer attempted the ſetting of corne, made the firſt holes with his finger. But this courſe being afterwards found to be very long and tedious, an inſtrument was deuiſed, hauing many teeth or pinnes, like a rake, with a ſtaffe faſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the middeſt of the backſide thereof, which being thruſt into the ground, did at one inſtant make twelue or twentie holes more or leſſe, according to the number of teeth or pinnes therein. Afterwardes this toole was alſo diſliked, as not making ſufficient riddance of ground, and in place thereof a boord of three foote or thereabout in length, and twelue or ten inches in breadth, was thought vpon, hauing diuers holes boared therein, according to ſuch diſtance as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery particular man beſt fanſied, through each of which holes a wodden dibber or pinne was thruſt into the ground, being of the bigneſſe of ones fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and of three or foure inches in length, hauing a ſhoulder or hole with a croſſe pin, to keepe one ſelfe ſame certaintie in the depth of each hole. The laſt deuiſe that as yet hath come to my view (but now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected, becauſe in the drawing out of ſo many pinnes the holes doe choake) is a boord of the ſame largenes with the former, driuen full of round pinnes of three or foure inches deepe within the boord, and placed
<pb facs="tcp:3712:6"/>each from other in equall diſtance by a true proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which at one impreſſion maketh ſo many recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacles for the corne, as there bee pinnes in the boord. Theſe boords are directed by a Gardiners line, firſt ſtrained to ſome reaſonable length, or by the eye, and thereby a ſtraight courſe is kept in the ſetting. When each hole hath receiued a corne, then muſt you rake ouer the ground to fill vp thoſe holes with earth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: and during all the time of ſetting and raking, you muſt ſtand or kneele vpon one of your boords, which you muſt remoue from place to place, as your ſetting and raking from time to time requires.</p>
               <p>Heere for the ſatisfaction of the ſimple, I haue thought good alſo to ſet downe the length of your boordes, together with the true boaring of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene each hole: and therefore if you haue fiue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches diſtance, then may you in a boord of ten inches broad make two rowes of holes, the firſt and laſt hole being two inches and a halfe from each ſide, and if the length thereof be two foote and eleuen inches, then may it well containe two rowes of holes, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſeuen holes in euerie rowe, the firſt and laſt hole being diſtant from each end two inches and a halfe: and when the ends or ſides of two ſuch boords ſo bored, ſhall bee laid together, they will make a true continuance of one ſelfe ſame skantling and diſtance of fiue inches through all your workes: if you worke vpon foure inches, then leaue at each ſide and end of your boord two inches: and ſo in a boord of three foote in length, and one foote in breadth, you ſhall haue nine holes in each row one way, and three holes the other way.</p>
               <p>And it is to be remembred that euerie two worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb facs="tcp:3712:6"/>(whereof the one maketh the holes, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſetteth the graine) muſt haue two boords to work vpon: and yet ſome be of opinion, that one man may performe both the works.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 5.</hi> At what depth and distance your corne muſt be ſet.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue beene enformed that the obſeruation of three inches deepe, and three inches diſtance, hath brought forth 30. quarters of wheat vpon one acre of ground, and that foure inches in depth, and foure in diſtance hath yeelded but twentie quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: happily the ground or the ſeede corne might make the difference. Some ſpeake of fiue inches deep and fiue in diſtance, with exceeding great encreaſe: the true finding out of which proportions may eaſily be obtained by ſeuerall trials made at ſeuerall depths and diſtances together, at one time, and in one ſelfe ſame peece of ground. Only heere I muſt remember you of that which was ſpoken of before, in the title of digging, chap. 3. that concerning the depth, you muſt haue an eſpeciall care, that your ſeed may lie within the rich cruſt of the earth, and that his bed wherein he lyeth, may alſo bee of the ſame goodneſſe, or elſe the plough will diſcredite the ſpade.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:3712:7"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 6.</hi> Whether it be good to fill the holes with common earth, and to prepare the ſeed before it be ſet.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the ground be a rich and kindly wheate ground, you ſhall find a ſufficient increaſe by filling them vp with their owne proper mould: for ſo haue the greateſt and moſt vſuall trials beene hitherto made alreadie; yet ſome pregnant wits, deſirous to exault nature to the higheſt degree of perfection, haue attempted the filling vp of thoſe holes both with Pigeons dung, ſheeps dung, and cow dung, and ſuch like, but with no good ſucceſſe at all, <hi>quaere</hi> if this dung had been firſt rotted into per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect earth and then beſtowed. Neither doe I ſee any reaſon in fat and luſtie grounds, why any further en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe ſhould bee ſought for then hath been found already, for that the earth is not able to carrie a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter burthen, then ſhe hath borne of late by theſe vſuall practiſes which haue been made. But in barren and ſpent grounds, it were greatly to be wiſhed, that by ſome artificiall and cheape meanes, a plentifull croppe of corne might be had and obtained. For the better furtherance whereof, I leaue theſe few conceits to the fauorable conſideration of thoſe, whoſe farmes are greater then mine, and haue had more familiar con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with nature then my ſelfe, referring them alſo farther both vnto the literall and ſecret ſence of my booke of Husbandrie before mentioned. And here I thinke it not amiſſe to cite in the firſt place that lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and poeticall Husbandman, who in his firſt booke of his Georgickes hath theſe Hexamiters.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3712:7"/>
               <q>
                  <l>Semina vidi equidem multos medicare ſerentes</l>
                  <l>Et nitro prius, &amp; nigra perfundere amurca:</l>
                  <l>Grandior vt foetus ſiliquis fallacibus eſſet,</l>
                  <l>Et quamuis igni exiguo<note n="*" place="margin">Citò coque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentur.</note> properata maderent;</l>
                  <l>Vidi laeta diu &amp; multo<note n="*" place="margin">Probata.</note> ſpectata labore</l>
                  <l>Degenerare tamen: ni vis humana quotannis,</l>
                  <l>Maxima quaeque manu legeret, &amp;c.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Here we ſee Salniter and the mother or Lees of oyle commended: but whether <hi>Virgill</hi> doe meane a ſteep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or imbibition of the graine in the Lees of oyle, wherein there hath beene a ſolution of Niter, or the corne onely ſprinkled ouer with them both in the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; it is left to the conſideration of the reader. But howſoeuer he intend the ſame, our countrie doth nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther afforde ſtore of Niter, nor yet of Amurca, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme many (if any) acres therewith; and though it did, yet would it proue a worke of greater charge and trouble (as I ſuppoſe) then would be endured: vnleſſe it were in ſome ſmall practiſe, and for the triall of a magiſterie, or vpon ſome richer ſeede then wheat, which in leſſe quantity would proue more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable then any ordinary graine, whereof there are ſome fewe of Engliſh breede, if I bee not decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</p>
               <p>But now let vs leaue <hi>Virgill</hi> to his poeticall vaine, and let vs come to that glorious Neapolitaine <hi>Iohan. Baptiſta Porta,</hi> who expecteth a generall applauſe of the whole world, for his laſt and learned booke of <hi>Magia naturalis</hi> (as in his preface to the reader, by a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capitulation of all his infinite readings, charges, and conferences with the greateſt clarkes of his time, he would intimate vnto vs) and waſhing our eyes firſt
<pb facs="tcp:3712:8"/>in Eyebright water, let vs ſee whether we are able to pierce and penetrate into theſe thicke and foggie clowdes of skill, which he hath in ſo many cloſe and figuratiue termes (as willing to vaunt of his owne wit, but vnwilling to benefit others) ſo ſtrangely deliuered vnto vs. I finde in the latter end of his third booke, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled <hi>de nouis plantis producendis,</hi> and ouer the 21. chapter, this ſuperſcription.</p>
               <q>Quomodo fruges ſatis amplo foenore exſatu colligamus, &amp; è vineis vinum.</q>
               <p>Whereupon he diſcourſeth in manner following: <hi>Vt luculentam, ſatiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> exoptatam coronidem huic noſtro li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bro imponeremus, docebimus quomodo frumentacea, &amp; le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumina ſatis amplo foenore è ſatu colligamus, &amp; è vineis vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num. Res profecto immenſae vtilitatis, vt ex vno modio plus centuplo proueniat. Sed ne quis, quod centuplum plus acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piet, dixerim, putet velim hunc exactum modiorum nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ex vno ſato collecturum: nam anno, coelo, ſolo, &amp; ſyde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus renuentibus, minor erit collectio, ſed non tam minor, quin quintuplo vſitatum non ſuperet; at his fauentibus, ex vno modio centeni quinquageni reddentur. Sed pollicitatio haec noſtra aliquibus paradoxum videbitur, ſed ſi ſanae men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis eſſent, maximum profecto videri deberet paradoxum, cur ex ſato ſemodio ducentos modios non recipiamus, quum ex ſato, &amp; concepto acino, videamus radicem in multiplices &amp; numeroſos culmos fructificare, plus minus quindecim, &amp; in ſpica ſexaginta grana contineri? mitto Byzacij Africae ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum Plinij, quod vno grano quadringenta paucis minus ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina miſerit, miſit<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ex eo loco procurator Neroni</hi> CCCXL. <hi>ſtipulas ex vno grano. Sed cauſam venemur, vnde id accide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re poſsit. Sunt qui dicant id euenire, quod pars maior iacti fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti
<pb facs="tcp:3712:8"/>ex volucribus, talpis, vermibus, alijſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſubterraneis animalibus deuoretur. Sed id falſum arguitur, quod ex ſato lupini modio non plus minus quindecim recipiuntur, quin lupinum impunè iaceat derelictum, ab omnibus animalibus ſua ingrata amaritudine tutum, &amp; ſuis in thecis, vaginuliſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> plus minus centum grana contineantur. Sunt alij, qui id eoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo aſcribant, frigorum, calorum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> iniurijs, vel imbrium fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentijs, vt nunc torpeant gelu arua, nunc ſiti infeſtentur, nunc in herbarum copiam luxurient, nunc macie intabeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant; ſed hoe falſum congruit argumentum, quod exmaxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo coelifauore, neque ex vno triceni redduntur. Sed ne lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us euagemur, dicimus non omnia ſpicae &amp; vaginulae grana naſci, nam alia Deus ad eſcam animalium, alia adſemen de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinauit. Sunt in ſpicis grana; quaſi abortus &amp; degeneres foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, quae non foeticant ſed deſciſcunt in vitium. Sunt quae è glumis in ſpicis emicant habitiora, quae ad propagationem producuntur. Praeterea nec debito tempore ſeruntur, deſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>untur<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> debito agricolarum opere: vnde ſi his obuiabimus; omnia ex voto ſuccedent. Semina enim prolixioribus radici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus implexis, longè latéque ſub tellure ſerpentibus, numero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiores culmos deproment, circumundi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſpicis vallatis. Spon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa ergo ſuo viro ducatur, non ex primis vel vltimis natis ſed è medijs, quia imbecilles ſunt, ac balneo ſecreta &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis delibuta &amp; pingui depaſta caprarum veterum Vulca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no, &amp; Baccho aſſociata cubile molle, &amp; optimè ſtratum ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefiat: viuifico enim calore in amicam naturam coeunt, &amp; dulcioribus amplexibus ſtringuntur &amp; haerent. Sic animata viro ſemina, non degenerem, ſed legitimam prolem donent. Suo foecundo lumine Luna praeſit, nam ferax feracem reddit, id reſtat praemonendum, vxorem Baccho ducendam non ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pillis deſtitutam, nam ſuo decore capite deſtituto ſpernitur à viro ſponſa, neque haberet, quo noxia purgarentur, ſed ſolum cincinnis orbetur; ſic enim minus compta, plus ſuo placebit
<pb facs="tcp:3712:9"/>&amp; viro.</hi> Which for the better vnderſtanding of ſuch as are no Latiniſts, I haue thought good to tranſlate into our naturall language, as followeth.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>How by ſetting and planting of Corne or vines; a great and plentifull encreaſe may be had.</head>
                  <p>That now at length, according to mine own deſire, I may ſhut vp this booke of plantes with a moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and renowmed concluſion, I will heere declare how all kinde of corne and pulſe, together with the vines themſelues ſhall recompence all our labours with great encreaſe. A matter without all queſtion of ſingular profite, to receiue more then an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred buſhels for one. But leaſt I bee miſtaken in this great proportion, I would not haue any man to thinke, that I doe heere ſet downe anie exact number of buſhels, from which nature can at no time varie: for if the yeare, the heauens, and the ground it ſelfe, together with the fatall influence of the ſtarres, doe all conſpire together, the number of our buſhels will fall ſhort, but neuer ſo ſhort, but that they will by fiue degrees exceede the accuſtomed yeeld. But if all theſe concurre and affoord their ſeuerall fauours, then may we wel expect 150. buſhels of one. But this proud promiſe of ours may happily ſeeme a paradox vnto ſome, vnto whom, if they were of any ſound &amp; ſharpe iudgement, it ſhould rather ſeeme a greater paradoxe, why halfe a buſhell ſhould not rather giue 200. hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred buſhels againe, when as we doe often ſee, that one corne being ſet and well rooted, doth ſtemme vp into diuers ſtalkes, yea ſometimes to the number of fifteene, more or leſſe, each eare alſo containing
<pb facs="tcp:3712:9"/>threeſcore cornes within it. I doe heere omit to ſpeake of Bizatium, that fruitfull ground of Africa, whereof <hi>Plinie</hi> maketh mention, where out of one corne foure hundred ſtalkes did braunch: and the Gouernour of that place did alſo ſend to <hi>Nero</hi> 240. ſtemmes ariſing from one graine. But let vs ſeeke out and hunt after the true reaſon hereof. Some be of opinion, that the cauſe why the ſame fertilitie doth not happen in our vſuall and ordinarie manner of ſowing, is, for that a great part of the ſeede which is ſowne, is deuoured by the foules of the ayre, by Moles, wormes and other cree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping creatures within the ground. But this is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtlie diſproued in the ſowing of Lupines, whereas ſeldome we do reape little more or leſſe then fifteene buſhels for one, although the ſame be ſo bitter a kinde of pulſe, that none of all theſe deuouring creatures will once touch it, but lieth ſafe within his hoſe, each codde containing much about an hundred graines: ſome attribute the ſame vnto the heauens, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries ariſing of heate, colde, and continuall ſhowres of raine, that doe often happen; ſo as ſometimes the grounds are benummed with froſts, and ſometimes parched with heat, ſomtime they make a rich &amp; fertile ſhew, and ſometimes they wither and waxt barren; but all this is eaſilie conuinced. For that admitting that the heauens doe afford all their fauourable influences at once, yet doe wee ſcarce obtaine at any time thirtie for one. But now to come neerer to our purpoſe, we doe affirme that each corne that is found within the eare is not apt to grow, for God hath created ſome of them for the foode of liuing creatures, and ſome for ſeede corne. There be in euery eare certaine abortiue and baſtardlie cornes, which will neuer fructifie, but
<pb facs="tcp:3712:10"/>become vtterly vnprofitable; and in ſome eares there are cornes which are more beautifull to behold then the reſt, which nature hath ordained for propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation. Beſides all this, the ſeed it ſelfe is not alwayes ſowne by the husbandman in his due time, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath it all his due rites and ceremonies per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourmed. So that if we can meete with all theſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections and errours, then will all good ſucceſſe follow, according to our owne hearts deſire. For the rootes being large in ſpreading vnder the ground, and each imbracing other in their manifold wrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things, will thereby ſend forth a greater number of ſtemmes, beſet and garniſhed with eares on euerie ſide. For the better accompliſhment whereof let the bridegrome make choice of ſuch a wife as is of the middle ſort, and not of the firſt or laſt borne, becauſe they are of a weaker conſtitution, let them both goe into a warme bath, and there annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting themſelues with ſweete ointment, and with the fatte food of old Goates, being mixed with <hi>Bacchus</hi> and <hi>Vulcan;</hi> let their ſoft and euen layd bed bee gently warmed: for by that viuifying heat they will vnite themſelues in an amiable maner, and bee knit and ioyned together in moſt ſweet and louing im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracements: and the ſeede being thus quickened by the powerfull heate of the man, will in the end bring forth a kindly, and no baſtardly iſſue: Let the Moone be predominant with her proſperous light, for ſhee being fruitfull, will alſo make the ſame to fructifie the better. But yet I muſt admoniſh you of one thing more, that ſuch a wife as is fitte for God <hi>Bacchus,</hi> muſt not bee bald and without haire, for ſo wanting the due ornament of her head,
<pb facs="tcp:3712:10"/>ſhee might happily be deſpiſed of her husband, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould ſhee haue whereat to purge her owne excrements, onely let all curlings and perriwigs bee laid aſide, that ſo being the more retchleſſe in her at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, ſhee may ſeeme more pleaſing and acceptable to her husband.</p>
                  <p>And what if all this myſticall marriage betweene God <hi>Bacchus</hi> and the Goddeſſe <hi>Ceres</hi> (at the ſolemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zation whereof onely <hi>Vuloan</hi> and <hi>Luna</hi> were preſent, as though neither <hi>Saturne, Iupiter, Mars, Sol, Venus,</hi> nor <hi>Mercury,</hi> nor the reſt of that celeſtiall crewe were neither worthie to dine nor daunce at the Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding) what, I ſay, if all this great myſterie or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſterie of nature, as <hi>Baptiſta Porta</hi> would haue it to appeare, bee nothing els but a ſoking of corne in wine, or in the new muſt thereof, before it bee ſet? Might not this without the prophaning of Nature, or her ſacred Maximes beene ſafely and without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence in plaine termes deliuered to the publike view of the worlde? But let vs examine the particulars of this parable. The wife (he ſaith) muſt neither be of the firſt nor laſt, but taken out of the middeſt: and here, becauſe hee ſhall be his owne expoſitor, I referre you to his ſecrete for enlarging of the Gourd, pag. 137. where he citeth theſe verſes out of <hi>Columella,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Siue globoſi</l>
                     <l>Corporis atque vtero nimium quae vaſta tumeſcit</l>
                     <l>Ventre legas medio, ſobolem dabit illa capacem.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>And this, ſaith <hi>Porta,</hi> is not onely to bee obſerued in this plant, but in all others likewiſe, for thoſe ſeedes which are contained within the middeſt of the
<pb facs="tcp:3712:11"/>bulke are more perfect themſelues, and bring forth more perfect plants then thoſe weake and imperfect ones, which occupie the outtermoſt places; and ſo the graine, hee ſaith, in the middle of the eare bringeth forth a larger corne then thoſe which growe in the toppe or bottome thereof.</p>
                  <p>Concerning the bath and ointment wherein <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can</hi> and <hi>Bacchus</hi> are vſed, I thinke he meaneth ſome fat temper made with cowdung or Goates dung, the older the better, moiſtened with wine or new muſt, whereby <hi>Bacchus</hi> is ſignified, in whom the ſecret fire and heate, which he holdeth, may alſo reſemble <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can,</hi> vnder whoſe name fire is ſometimes ſignified, as in that ſaying of <hi>Paracelſus, In Vulcano veritas:</hi> and in this compound, the goddeſſe <hi>Ceres</hi> is lapped before ſhe be ſet into the ground; or elſe the ground and mixture are after watered with wine, or elſe the corne is firſt ſteeped a certaine time in wine before the graine is beſtowed in the earth: any of theſe conſtructions ſeeme probable, and to haue ſome affinitie with his fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guratiue tearmes.</p>
                  <p>Her bed muſt bee very ſoft, and delicately made, whereby he doth manifeſtly inſinuate the very dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging with the ſpade, which worketh the mould into a moſt fine and ſubtill bodie: the warming of the bed, and thoſe ſweete collings and clippings together are intended to be wrought with the moiſtning heate of <hi>Bacchus.</hi> It ſeemeth alſo that he would haue this ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting perfourmed in the increaſe, or toward the full of the Moone. The corne he would haue to bee ſet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with his chaffe about it, which he termeth the haire, whereby nature purgeth the excrement of the head, but not with the beard of the eare, which hath a
<pb facs="tcp:3712:11"/>curled kind of graine vpon it. Let this ſatisfie, that I haue aimed at the marke, the pinne being ſo farre off, and cleane out of ſight. But what ſhould we vexe our ſpirits in beating out the ſenſe of this myſticall La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, when as without all other circumſtance, wee ſee that one corne pricked into the ground, bringeth forth eyght hundreth cornes at once, whereas <hi>Porta</hi> ſpeaketh of two hundred only at the moſt, euen when heauen and earth doe all ioyne hand in hand toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to helpe his inuention? And who knoweth whether he miſtake the reaſon of his owne conceite, for happily the mellownes of the ground being ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and broken with the ſpade, did of it ſelfe performe the great wonder which he writeth of, and then both <hi>Bacchus</hi> and <hi>Ceres,</hi> and <hi>Luna</hi> may haue Iacke Drums entertainment.</p>
                  <p>Now if I were alſo diſpoſed to attire and diſguiſe a plaine ſecret in his figuratiue robes, what a deepe and drunken riddle could I here ſet downe of ſteeping barley or wheat in new ale in cornes (although I hold the wort, ſo it be of the firſt rap, to be much better) for this doth ſeeme to be his owne naturall bath, whereby it ſhould receiue a multiplying vertue in his owne kind? I feare to proſecute this ſecret any farther in ſuch Philoſophicall termes, leaſt ſome nouice in Alcumie ſhould ſuppoſe that I doe goe about to vnfold and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe the ſacred materials and working of the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers ſtone, and yet to ſpeake in good ſooth, I durſt vndertake to perfourme as much with ale or beere as <hi>Bap. Porta</hi> ſhall doe with his ſacke and ſugar, or Claret wine and Limons, let him make his choice.</p>
                  <p>And becauſe <hi>Virgil</hi> hath ſpoken of Niter, I haue though good alſo, as a Paralel to the ſame out of M.
<pb facs="tcp:3712:12"/>
                     <hi>Bar. Googe</hi> his booke of Husbandrie, fol. 33. b. to ſot downe the ſteeping of Beanes in the water wherein Salt Peter hath been diſſolued, and why not other graine and pulſe, as wel as Beanes? And thus you haue Rome &amp; Naples anſwered with Surrey and London, I pray God all may bring forth one good concluſion for our common-wealth of England.</p>
                  <p>But why ſhould we ſpend theſe coſtly liquors that are fitter for Tauernes &amp; Alehouſes, then for ruſticall imbibitions? when as with common water and the dung of cattell, eſpecially of Oxen, Kine, and Sheepe, or Pigeons dung (wherof more quantity, with a great deale leſſe charge (being not much inferior in effects) may ſo eaſily be had &amp; obtained) Then heare me with patience, &amp; if I happen to ſlip, ſtay me with a friendly band, and ſo happily I may ſaue ſome of you from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a dangerous fall. There is a great opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conceited, yea publikely maintained by good Authors in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueral books about imbibition of corne in ſome fat and fructifying liquors; but neither the ſtrength of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors, the time of imbibition, nor the proportion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the liquor &amp; graine, hath as yet bin thoroughly ſounded, nay ſcarſely touched by any; which three points I holde to be ſo materiall, ans that without the knowledge of them al in ſome good meaſure, nothing elſe but clamors againſt the writers, and errors in the practizers are like to enſue.</p>
                  <p>And firſt concerning the ſtrength of your liquor vpon your dung, you cannot lightly erre, ſo as you let the ſame reſt vpon a ſufficient quantity thereof, vntill it haue gotten a deep colour, and a ſtrong ſmel &amp; ſauour fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his ingredient: as ſuppoſe you put two parts water to one third part of dung, ſuffering the ſame to infuſe
<pb facs="tcp:3712:12"/>foure or fiue daies, and ſtirring the ſame once or twice euery day, till it haue gotten out all the hart &amp; ſtrength of the dung, or ſo much therof as the water is able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after ſome ſetling, ſtrain this liquor through ſome courſe cloth, &amp; if it will not run, then adde more water vnto it, for here your ſpeciall care muſt be, that your liquor do not grow too thicke: after al this, let the ſame repoſe 12. or 24. houres, &amp; then gently dreine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the cleere from the grounds or feticall reſidence, and ſo haue you a liquor ſufficiently prepared to ſteep your corne in: &amp; for the better performa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce hereof, you may boare a hole within an inch of the bottome of the veſſel, or halfe an inch, according as you ſhal ſee y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame to run cleere &amp; not muddy into your receiuing veſſel.</p>
                  <p>And as for the time of imbibition, it is a rule in natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Philoſophle, that euery thing hath his ſtomacke, which doth neuer leaue drawing &amp; attracting vnto it ſelfe ſuch matter as is apt for it, vntil it be glutted; and then as being ouercharged, it loatheth and ſpueth out euen that which otherwiſe it moſt deſireth: as it doth manifeſtly appeare in the ſtomacke of man, wherin by ouergorging it ſelf a <hi>Nauſea</hi> doth preſently enſue. This is yet made more manifeſt in the art of dying, where, if in your blewes and greenes you worke with Indico, or in Stammels, Crimſons, Carnations or Scarlets, you worke with Greine or Kutcheneele, the cloth when it hath receiued his glut of colour, though neuer ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten dipped after, wil nothing at al exalt it ſelfe in beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or richnes of colour; euen ſo it fareth with corne, after it hath imbibed ſo much liquor, as it can well beare and brooke without breaking of the hull, the is it time to dreine away the water: and yet wee ſee, that Peaſe, though they bee ſteeped till
<pb facs="tcp:3712:13"/>they ſprowt a little, that they will grow notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, I leaue the aduenturing of wheate and barlie ſo farre vnto them, that liſt by often and manifold triall to ſearch for the period of this practiſe.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, for the better finding out of a true proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on betweene the corne and your liquor: firſt, put your corne in the veſſell, and adde ſo much of your fat li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor vnto it as will couer the ſame. And if the corne drinke it vp, then adde more liquor thereunto: and the onely feare in this worke, is leaſt if you ouercharge your corne with water, that the water will rather draw the ſtrength from the corne, then the corne draw ſtrength from the water</p>
                  <p>And thus I haue diſcouered the true vſe of all imbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitions: which haue hitherto been confirmed by ſome, and condemned by others, each ſeuerall man reporting according to his owne experience. But the errours may from henceforth be eaſily preuented by a carefull obſeruation of theſe few rules alreadie deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered in as plaine and ſimple a maner (as reſpecting the generall good, which was the <hi>primum mobile</hi> of this Diſcourſe) I could poſſibly deuiſe or publiſh.</p>
                  <p>Heere I thinke it not impertinent to our purpoſe to ſet downe ſeuerall means for the enriching of ground, the trials whereof, by way of imbibition, I referre to each mans patticular experience.</p>
                  <p>Sea Kilpes and ſea Tangle, and other ſea weeds are found by experience to enrich both arable and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture grounds exceedingly. Shreds of woollen cloth ſtrewed vpon paſture ground will bring forth graſſe abundantly.</p>
                  <p>The dregs of beere and ale applyed to the rootes of trees, and other ſmaller plants, will make them
<pb facs="tcp:3712:13"/>flouriſh and proſper mightilie, Seeds ſteeped in brine, proportioned according to Sea water, which conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth of one part ſalte, and eyghteene or twentie parts water, wil in diuers grounds procure a good encreaſe.</p>
                  <p>The Soote of Chimnies, both ingendred by Sea-coale, as alſo by wood and charcoale in a very ſmall quantitie, worketh great effects this way.</p>
                  <p>There is a ſalte which the Petermen vpon the refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of their Peter, doe ſeparate from the Peter, this ſalte (if I be not deceiued) is the ſalte purchaſed from the aſhes, vpon which the Petermen powre their fog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie liquors to cleere them; one worke (vnles it be a great one) doth not yeelde much aboue a buſhell thereof weekely: this ſalte I take to be a trew vegetable ſalte, and therefore exceeding profitable, either to be ſtrewed vpon grounds to be mixed amongſt the ſeede corne, or for imbibition.</p>
                  <p>Shauings of horne, vpon mine owne experience, I muſt of neceſſitie commend, by the meanes whereof, I obtained a moſt flouriſhing garden at Biſhops hall, in a moſt barren and vnfruitfull plot of ground, which none of my Predeceſſors could euer grace or beautifie either with knots or flowres.</p>
                  <p>I haue had the like experience with ſingular good ſucceſſe by ſtrewing the waſte ſope aſhes vpon a bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of ſommer Barlie, whereof three eares would haue counterpeized any fiue that euer came to my ſight: you may ſee a plentifull diſcourſe of theſe ſope aſhes in my booke of husbandrie.</p>
                  <p>Some commend greatly the watering of ground preſently after it is ſowne, with an artificial Brine, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of an eyghteenth or twentith part of ſalte: this is performed by a hogſhed or ſome other ſuch like veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell
<pb facs="tcp:3712:14"/>drawne vpon a ſled, hauing one of the heads boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red full of ſmall hoales like a watring pot.</p>
                  <p>The reſidence or grounds of the Oad fat, ſerue alſo to enrich ground with.</p>
                  <p>Malte duſt may heere alſo challenge his place: for foure or fiue quarters thereof, are ſufficient for an acre of ground.</p>
                  <p>The hulles which are diuided from the Oates, in the making of Oatmeale, either in their owne preſent nature, or being burnt to aſhes, make an excellent ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance for enriching of ground. Fearne either rotted to dung by a mixture of earth amongſt it, or conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with fire into aſhes, maketh a ſingular ſoile to lay vpon barren and hungrie grounds.</p>
                  <p>When the Iron ſtone or oare is burnt, thoſe fine aſhes that are ſifted from the ſame, doe proue a moſt excellent ſubſtance for the enriching of wet mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, or Mariſh groundes, eſpeciallie ſuch as are ruſhie, ſlaggie, or ſedgie, and will bring the ſame to a fine ſweete graſſe: you ſhall finde the ground euery yeare better than other, with a manifeſt and apparant difference betweene that parcell of your ground which you haue enriched therewith, and all the reſt of the ſame field, both by the glorious greene colour which it carrieth, and alſo by the delight of the cattell continuallie feeding thereon, and refuſing the other till that be ſpent. There is plentie of this matter to be had in Suſſex, Eſſex, Wales, and ſuch other ſhires wherein there hath been any long continuance of yron workes, and thoſe hils which conſiſt of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter are worth the breaking vp, though they be aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and haue lien long vncouered; but the beſt and hartieſt, is that which hath been kept alwaies couered
<pb facs="tcp:3712:14"/>and defended from the raine: this kinde of ſoyle is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo good for wheate ground, and three loades thereof are a ſufficient proportion for one acre: and if you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the ſame for graſſe, you muſt ſpread it vpon the ground about alhallountide. The light of this ſecret I receiued from a Yorkeſhire Gentleman, a man both of great gifts and great poſſeſſions, who aſſured me of three yeares triall made by himſelfe with very good ſucceſſe, whoſe opinion is, that three loads thereof will enrich one acre of ground for ſeuen yeeres at the leaſt.</p>
                  <p>Sal Armoniake being a volatile ſalt, firſt incorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and rotted in common earth, is thought to be a rich molde to plant or ſet in (<hi>quaere</hi> of ſteeping graine in water, hauing a trew proportion thereof firſt diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in it) but he that can proue ſo fortunate as to finde out the trew Sal Armoniake of mettall, ſhall be able with ſmall quantitie to worke great wonders in this kinde.</p>
                  <p>Dogges and Cats, and other beaſtes, and general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly all carrion buried vnder the rootes of Trees, in a due time will make them flouriſh and bring forth fruite in great abundance.</p>
                  <p>Here I cannot omit a ſtrange ſecret deliuered by a Gentleman of good worth vnto mee, euen before this worke was fullie perfected, which I haue reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for the concluſion of this title. Hee aſſured mee of a gentleman, at this preſent dwelling in Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall, who being very induſtrious, and ſearching into the workes of Nature, would needes attempte the ſowing of Wheate in his arable groundes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſuch kinde, nature and qualitie, as was meerely repugnant and vnfit for that graine, as the experience
<pb facs="tcp:3712:15"/>ſell drawne vpon a ſled, hauing one of the heads boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red full of ſmall hoales like a watring pot.</p>
                  <p>The reſidence or grounds of the Oad fat, ſerue alſo to enrich ground with.</p>
                  <p>Malte duſt may heere alſo challenge his place: for foure or fiue quarters thereof, are ſufficient for an acre of ground.</p>
                  <p>The hulles which are diuided from the Oates, in the making of Oatmeale, either in their owne preſent nature, or being burnt to aſhes, make an excellent ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance for enriching of ground. Fearne either rotted to dung by a mixture of earth amongſt it, or conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with fire into aſhes, maketh a ſingular ſoile to lay vpon barren and hungrie grounds.</p>
                  <p>When the Iron ſtone or oare is burnt, thoſe fine aſhes that are ſifted from the ſame, doe proue a moſt excellent ſubſtance for the enriching of wet mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, or Mariſh groundes, eſpeciallie ſuch as are ruſhie, ſlaggie, or ſedgie, and will bring the ſame to a fine ſweete graſſe: you ſhall finde the ground euery yeare better than other, with a manifeſt and apparant difference betweene that parcell of your ground which you haue enriched therewith, and all the reſt of the ſame field, both by the glorious greene colour which it carrieth, and alſo by the delight of the cattell continuallie feeding thereon, and refuſing the other till that be ſpent. There is plentie of this matter to be had in Suſſex, Eſſex, Wales, and ſuch other ſhires wherein there hath been any long continuance of yron workes, and thoſe hils which conſiſt of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter are worth the breaking vp, though they be aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and haue lien long vncouered; but the beſt and hartieſt, is that which hath been kept alwaies couered
<pb facs="tcp:3712:15"/>and defended from the raine: this kinde of ſoyle is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo good for wheate ground, and three loades thereof are a ſufficient proportion for one acre: and if you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the ſame for graſſe, you muſt ſpread it vpon the ground about alhallountide. The light of this ſecret I receiued from a Yorkeſhire Gentleman, a man both of great gifts and great poſſeſſions, who aſſured me of three yeares triall made by himſelfe with very good ſucceſſe, whoſe opinion is, that three loads thereof will enrich one acre of ground for ſeuen yeeres at the leaſt.</p>
                  <p>Sal Armoniake being a volatile ſalt, firſt incorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and rotted in common earth, is thought to be a rich molde to plant or ſet in (<hi>quaere</hi> of ſteeping graine in water, hauing a trew proportion thereof firſt diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in it) but he that can proue ſo fortunate as to finde out the trew Sal Armoniake of mettall, ſhall be able with ſmall quantitie to worke great wonders in this kinde.</p>
                  <p>Dogges and Cats, and other beaſtes, and general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly all carrion buried vnder the rootes of Trees, in a due time will make them flouriſh and bring forth fruite in great abundance.</p>
                  <p>Here I cannot omit a ſtrange ſecret deliuered by a Gentleman of good worth vnto mee, euen before this worke was fullie perfected, which I haue reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for the concluſion of this title. Hee aſſured mee of a gentleman, at this preſent dwelling in Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall, who being very induſtrious, and ſearching into the workes of Nature, would needes attempte the ſowing of Wheate in his arable groundes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſuch kinde, nature and qualitie, as was meerely repugnant and vnfit for that graine, as the experience
<pb facs="tcp:3712:16"/>of the greateſt part of the Countrie round about him did manifeſtly declare. And this he performed onely by infuſing his ſeede corne foure and twentie houres in a ſtrong liquor, that had deſcended from his muck-heape into a receptacle of bricke: but he neuer infuſed his corne (as I am informed) till the liquor had been of two yeares date, and he alwaies dried his corne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſowed it: <hi>quaere</hi> if in leſſe time and without dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the ſame effects will not follow.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 7.</hi> How to make choice of your ſeed corne.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Vch corne as is rubbed betweene ones hands out of the middle of the eare, the vpper and neather part therof being firſt diuided, I hold (with <hi>Bap. Porta</hi>) to be the moſt fruitfull ſeed of all the reſt, and that the hand, though it bee a more labour-ſome worke, doth performe this better than the flaile, which maketh no diuiſion of the graine, and yet brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth a great part thereof by the violence of the ſtroke. But if your threſhed wheat content you, then is it beſt either to picke each corne by it ſelfe, and ſo to diuide the good from the bad (which is a fit worke for chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and may the rather be endured, for that ſo ſmall a proportion of ſeed will ſerue to ſet an acre, viz. 12. pintes thereof, if each graine be at ſiue inches diſtance, as ſome haue obſerued) or els to powre your corne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a tubbe of water, ſtirring it vp and downe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the beſt and heauieſt cornes will ſinke to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, and the lighteſt graine will fleete and flote in the toppe, which may eaſily be ſeuered. I know no other meanes ſeruing for the choice of your ſeed corne, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb facs="tcp:3712:16"/>thoſe which are ſo vſuall and common; as that they deſerue no place amongſt new inuentions, and therefore I do here aduiſedly omit to touch or name them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 8.</hi> The difference of yeeld betweene the plough and the ſpade, with ſome new addition to the plough.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E that reapeth foure quarters of wheate out of one acre by his plough, doth hold himſelfe well contented, as with a rich croppe, which is eight at the leaſt for one. I know the greateſt number do ſcarcely attaine ſeuen for one, and many but ſix for one: but if he haue ten or twelue for one, then hee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth himſelfe to haue receiued an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary fauour and bleſſing from the heauens: yet (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe both happily, and by credible report it is come to my hands) I will heere ſet downe one rare experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment perfourmed this laſt yeare with the plough, wherein no doubt the Actor did ſtriue euen in the ſtrength of his wit and ſpirit to make the beſt imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which he could of the ſpade. The ground hauing a naturall declining or deſcent by his owne ſcituation, was firſt croſſe ploughed with a very deepe cutting plough, and then ploughed ouer the third time with a ſhallow plough, that made very cloſe &amp; narrow fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes; then was the ſeede ſowne by a skilfull ſower, and then harrowed ouer; and by this newe practiſe the owner obtained 15. quarters (I dare not ſay 20.) vpon each acre which hee ſowed. I doe not cite this ſtrange &amp; admirable experiment, either to ouerthrow the whole frame of my former worke, by vndermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the foundation thereof, or to hinder the labours
<pb facs="tcp:3712:17"/>of ſo many thouſands of poore and diſtreſſed people, which by digging and ſetting are like to be profitably employed in this land by meanes of the ſpade (whoſe eſtates with all Chriſtian commiſeration I doe pitie, and am willing to relieue) but profeſſing all the good I can, and by all the meanes that I may, to aduaunce the common good of the whole realme, &amp; knowing that if this new practiſe of digging by good ſucceſſe thereof do happen to become generall in and ouer the whole land, notwithſtanding the realme be po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous, &amp; ſurcharged with infinite numbers of poore men, women, and children, and maimed ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that yet there will ſcarcely be found workemen e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for the tenth acre of land: I ſay, for the better increaſe of all ſuch grounds where the plough muſt of neceſſitie be vſed, I was bold to inſert this inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to ſupply the defect of labourers, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of neceſſitie would enſue. And yet if I may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue thoſe infinite reports, which are now with open trumpet ſounded into each mans eare, in commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſpade, there will be no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon betweene the plough &amp; it, though all men would ioyne all their wits together for the better furtherance thereof; out of many of which reports, I will only reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber theſe few.</p>
               <p>A Iuſtice of Peace &amp; Quorum of my acquaintance, dwelling in Eſſex, and deſirous to make a triall of that wonderfull experience, ſo commended at the Court of Requeſts barre by a Counſeller, who had ſeene the ſame the ſommer before, would needs ſet a parcell of ground with his owne hands, as ſoon as he came from Michaelmaſſe tearme laſt to his houſe: in Aprill the ſame began to ſhew verie greene and full of blade, and in harueſt time each corne brought forth at the leaſt
<pb facs="tcp:3712:17"/>27. eares, ſome 30. and ſome 32. with fortie graines in each eare, whoſe proportion is at the leaſt a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand for one. For the truth of which report, I dare gage my credit, I know the Gentleman to be ſo tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate and well aduiſed of his ſpeech.</p>
               <p>I doe heare of another Gentleman dwelling in Surrey, who hath reaped 16 buſhels out of one pint of wheat which he ſet, and that ſome cornes brought forth 40. &amp; ſome 48. eares hauing 66.68. &amp; 72. cornes in each eare, I could name the Gent. dwelling, &amp; place of the triall, but this which I ſpeake I dare warrant to be true, hauing good ground of credit for the ſame.</p>
               <p>In Northamptonſhire there grew barlie this laſt ſummer, amongſt the which there was found ſome rootes hauing 120. eares vpon one roote, with thirtie graines at the leaſt in each eare.</p>
               <p>I haue alſo heard by ſundry reports of 20.30. &amp; 32. quarters of wheat vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an acre, &amp; of 15. quarters of bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpon an acre; yea there haue been ſome which haue reported, that they haue had 15. quarters of wheat vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one acre by this maner of ſetting, the ground being ſpent and out of heart by often plowing before.</p>
               <p>And if I ſhould report all the ſeueral trials that haue beene made by ſeueral perſons, aſwel of the Nobility as others, within theſe two laſt yeares, I ſhould both weary my ſelfe with recording, and you with reading ſuch infinit numbers of practiſes as I could produce, <hi>ſed ex his reliqua.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I wil here either borrow leaue, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend without leaue, a new, light and portable Pumpe, being of late graced with her Maieſties moſt fauorable priuiledge, which I am bold to publiſh, together with this artifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry, becauſe I know no better means to giue a
<pb facs="tcp:3712:18"/>publike notice thereof vnto all my country men then by this pamphlet, which taking the wings of fame vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, is like to diſperſe both it ſelfe and his companion abroad in a moſt ſpeedy and ſodaine manner through all this litle Iland. This Pump is of wood, &amp; moueable from place to place by one mans labour: it is kept with verie ſmall charge in good reparations: it is cheape, and deliuereth great ſtore of water in a little time by his double ſtroke to a reaſonable height; it occupieth ſmall roome; it ſerueth to emptie Cellers and ponds; it is verie neceſſarie for all merchants ſhips, and other ſhips of warre, whereby all ſuperfluous water may bee ſafely conueied out at the neather port-holes in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>great leake happening by fight, or otherwiſe. But the moſt generall, vſe thereof (as I take it) will bee for all thoſe ſtately houſes and buildings which border vpon the riuer of Thames, or any other riuer, whereby they may receiue ſufficient ſtore of water to ſerue all their offices and gardens belonging to the ſame. You may heare farther of the Authour of this Inuention by the Printer hereof.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>H. PLAT Eſquire.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
